Finding Aid for the Donald Davie2 Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Academic Career, 1951-1988
  - Lecture Notes
    - Shakespeare -The Tempest (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Shakespeare -Troilus and Cressida I. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Shakespeare -Troilus and Cressida II. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Shakespeare -Sonnets (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Shenstone -Elegies (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Sidney -Apoligies for Poetrie (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Sidney -Arcadia (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Christopher Smart (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Robert Southwell (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Spenser -Faerie Queene I. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Spenser -Faerie Queene II. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Jonathan Swift I. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Jonathan Swift II. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Sterne (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Thackery -Vanity Fair (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Trollope -Barchester Towers (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Victorian Novel -The Introductory Lecture I. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Victorian Novel -Dickens II. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Victorian Novel -Dickens III. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Victorian Novelists -IV. Thackery (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Victorian Novelists -Charlotte Bronte (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Wordsworth and Some Contemporaries (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Professional Activities, 1972 - circa 1980
  - Recorded Readings
    - Donald Davie/Selected Poems (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Donald Davie reading John Dryden (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Donald Davie Interview for WPLN Nashville with Molly Howell, originally broadcast 21 May 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Davie, Donald. Contemporary Poets Reading Their Own Poetry. The British Council--Recorded Sound Section. Tape No. 1841-Dubbed 21 December 1972. 7 & ½ ips. Duration-28minutes, 37 seconds. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Film. 1800 feet, 7 " reel. Red label appended-reads "1-Stevenson-7 & 1/2." No other markings. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - PNR Materials - Editing
    - Editorial in PNR (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Galley proofs for various issues of PNR edited by Donald Davie (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Associates and Colleagues, 1969-1983
  - Warshaw, Howard
    - Correspondence from Howard Warshaw to Donald Davie (4) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - “Drawings on Drawing” by Howard Warshaw (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Whigham, Peter
    - Correspondences 1, 1982. An international review of literature; this copy belonged to Peter Whigham and announced publication of his work to appear in the next issue (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - “A Dante Portfolio” by Peter Whigham (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - “The Comedy of Dante Aligheri: Inferno Canto I.” Translated with notes on the translation by Peter Whigham. Inscribed (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Whigham, Peter. Do's and Don't's of Translation. California: Turkey Press, 1982. Inscribed. Inserted into the book are 2 photocopied pages of poems, without an author’s name or date. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Writings by Others, 1922-1987
  - About Donald Davie
    - Bernard Bergonzi. “The Poetry of Donald Davie.” The Critical Quarterly (2), 1962 Winter (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Clyde Binfield. “Another Note on Non-Conformists.” PNR, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - James A. Powell (with Paul Lake). “An Interview with Donald Davie.” Occident. Volume C, Number 2, Winter 1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Proof Copies Received for Review
    - Bush, Donald. T.S. Eliot: A Study in Character and Style. Oxford/New York: Oxford University Press, 1983. Uncorrected advance bound proofs for review. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Kenner, High. A Sinking Island: The Modern English Writers. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Lowell, Robert. Collected Prose. Uncorrected proof copy. Handwritten annotations by Davie, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Pritchard, William H. Frost: A Literary Life Reconsidered. Oxford/New York: Oxford University Press. Uncorrected advance bound proofs for review, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Robinson, Janice S. H.D.: The Life and Work of an American Poet. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, Uncorrected proof, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Student Poetry
    - Daniel, David. "Alternatives to Life." Photocopy of poems submitted for M.A. degree, Johns Hopkins University, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Daniel, David. 3 poems. (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - De Arajo, Virginia. Correspondence and Miscellaneous poems. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - De Arajo, Virginia. Miscellaneous poems a photocopy of Salvage, 1984. Inscribed note. Erinna. Trs., Daniel Haberman with Marilyn Arthur. Erinna to Baucis with an Epigram by Antipater of Sidon. New York, 1978. Private printing, copy 204 of 300. Inscribed., 1978-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - De Andrade, Carlos Drummond. Virginia de Arajo, tr. WPA # 9. The Word People (4 copies), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Hearne, Vicki. Nervous Horses. (62 pp. Of photocopied book). Letter from Hearne to Davie., undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Hearne, Vicki. Nervous Horses. Photocopy. Inscribed., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Hearne, Vicki. The Purebred Dog Gazette. Photocopy. Inscribed., undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Miller, Greg. American Flat. Photocopy of poetry ms. Sent to Davie along with a letter, 1985 August (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Miller, Greg. The Beautiful Broken Things. Photocopy of poetry ms, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Twentieth Century Poets and Authors
    - Bernstein, Michael Andre. "Robert Duncan: Talent and the Individual Tradition" Sagetrieb Vol. 4, nos. 2 & 3, Fall & Winter 1985 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bly, Robert. "The Woman Who Lives Forever." (New York, 1987). Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bryant, Kenneth. Posthumous (after Horace)---for Donald Davie. Typescript of poem, April, '88. Inscribed with initials., 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Brown, Mark W. Photocopy of archive material of Ivor Gurney transcribed by hand and annotated. File includes a note dated April 27, 1988. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Burchfield, Robert. The Spoken Language as an Art Form: An Autobiographical Approach. Occasional Papers 1, The English Speaking Union of the United States, May, 1981. Inscribed, July 1981. Includes inscribed note. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Chace, William M. "Lionel Trilling." The American Scholar. Winter, 1978/79. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Chandler, James K. "Wordsworth and Blake" ELH Vol. 47, 1980, pp. 741-771 (Johns Hopkins Univ. Press, 1980) (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Costa, Corrado. Paul Vangelisti, tr. Our Positions. California: The Red Hill Press, 1975. The first two poems have, under the original Italian, handwritten translations which differ from the Vangelisti translations on the facing pages. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Dekker, George. "Sir Walter Scott, the Angel of Hadley, and American Historical Fiction" American Studies Vol. 17, no. 2 (1982) (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - DiPalma, Ray. Plank. 1979. (Booklet of poetry). (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Doherty, Mary Jane. "Flores Solitudinis: The ‘Two Ways’ and Vaughan’s Patristic Hagiography”. George Herbert Journal Vol. 7, nos. 1 & 2, Fall 1983/Spring 1984 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Erinna. Translated by Daniel Haberman with Marilyn Arthur. Erinna to Baucis. With an epigram by Antipater of Sidon. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Flanner, Hildegarde. The Hearkening Eye. 1979. (Booklet of poetry). (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Gal, Istvan. "Sir Philip Sidney’s Guidebook to Hungary" Hungarian Studies in EnglishVol. 4, December 1969. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Gibbons, Reginald. The Poet's Work. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Co., 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Gibbons, Reginald. Miscellaneous poems in typescript and photocopies. Inscribed., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Goia, Dana. "An Elegy for Vladimir de Pachmann" The Hudson Review Vol. 34, no. 3, Autumn 1981 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Greene, Donald. "’Dramatic Texture’ in Pope" in From Sensibility to Romanticism: Essays in Honor of F.A. Pottle (Yale, 1965) (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Greene, Donald. "Latitudinarianism and Sensibility: The Genealogy of ‘The Man of Feeling’ Reconsidered" Modern Philology Vol. 75, no.2 Nov. 1977. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Greene, Donald. "The Study of Eighteenth-Century Literature: Past, Present, Future" in New Approaches to Eighteenth-Century Literature (Columbia Univ., 1974) (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Greene, Donald. "Western Canadian Literature" 1967. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Greene, Donald et al. Correspondence sent to Donald Davie. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Guerard, Maclin B. "Reflections in Advanced Middle Age" Women’s Studies Vol. 5, 1977. (Photocopy of Poem) Inscribed. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Gurney, Ivor. Photocopy of handwritten archive (poems and letters) of Ivor Gurney, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Gurney, Ivor. Photocopy of handwritten archive (poems and letters) of Ivor Gurney, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Jacobson, Roman. "On the Verbal Art of William Blake and Other Poet-Painters"Linguistic Inquiry, Vol. 1, no. 1, Jan. 1970. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Jacobson, Roman. ""Poetry of Grammar and Grammar of Poetry" Lingua: International Review of General Linguistics, Vol.21, 1968. (Offprint) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Kabdebo, Thomas and Paul Tabori, eds. A Tribute to Gyula Illyes. Washington: Occidental Press, 1968. Includes Donald Davie’s poem “At Plovdiv,” p. 35. Inserted into the book is a letter from Kabdebo to Davie (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Kreyling, Michael. "Lee Agonistes: The Southern Hero In the ‘Mid-Passage,’" The South Atlantic Quarterly Vol. 84, no. 4, Autumn 1985. (Offprint) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Lewis, Janet. Poems Old and New 1918-1977. Photocopy, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Matthias, John. Miscellaneous poems. Typescript and photocopy. Inscribed, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Menashe, Samuel. Poems: "The Bare Tree" Sept. 22, 1966 (Typescript mss. of Poems) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Menashe, Samuel. Poems: "The Bare Tree" Nov. 22, 1968 (Typescript mss. of Poems) Inscribed. (Water damaged) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Nemoianu, Virgil "Is Literature Always Reactionary?" The Georgia Review Vol. 37,No. 2, Summer 1983. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Nist, John. "Dulce and Decorum: An Epic of the American Civil War. Book One:The Peninsular Campaign" The Beloit Poetry Journal Vol. 9, Nos. 1 &2, Fall-Winter 1958. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Oberhaus, Dorothy Huff. " ‘Engine Against the Almightie’: Emily Dickinson and Prayer" ESQ, Vol. 32, 3rd Quarter, 1986. (Offprint). Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Oberhaus, Dorothy Huff. "’ Tender Pioneer’: Emily Dickinson’s Poems on the Life Of Christ" American Literature, Oct. 1987. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Occident. Vol. XCIX. No. 1, Fall, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Perloff, Marjorie. "Pound/Stevens: Whose Era?" New Literary History: A Journal Of Theory and Interpretation Vol. 13, 1982. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Pikoulis, John. "Scott and ‘Marmion’: The Discovery of Identity" The Modern Language Review Vol. 66, no. 4, October 1971 (Offprint) (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Pinkerton, Helen. "Celebration.” The Southern Review Vol. 12, no. 2, Spring, 1976 (Offprint of Poem) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Pinsky, Robert. Sadness and Happiness (Typed mss. of Pinsky’s first book of poetry) (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Pratt, William. "Imagism and Irony: The Shaping of the International Style" The South Atlantic Quarterly Vol. 83, no. 1, Winter 1984 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Ramsey, Paul, ed. Contemporary Religious Poetry. New Jersey: Paulist Press, 1987. Includes Donald Davie's poem, “Prime,” p. 160. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Ramsey, Paul. No Running on the Boardwalk. The University of Georgia Press. Inscribed., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Ramsey, Paul. Typescript mss. of poems sent to Davie to be considered for inclusion In The Oxford Book of Christian Verse. Also photocopy of poems published in Shenandoah, Vol. XXVI, no. 1, Fall 1974. Correspondence from Ramsey to Davie, 1979 October 21 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Reeves, Gareth. "The Waste Land and the Aeneid" Modern Language Review Vol. 82, no. 3, July 1987 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Sandeen, Ernest. Photocopies, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Shankman, Steven. "Led by the Light of the Maeonian Star: Aristotle on Tragedy and Odyssey 17.415-444" Classical Antiquity, Vol. 2, no. 1, April 1983 (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Shankman, Steven. "Reason and Revelation in the Pre-Enlightenment: Eric Vogelin’s Analysis and the Case of Swift" Religion and Literature, Vol. 16, no. 2, Summer, 1984. (Offprint) Inscribed. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Photocopy of "The Courtesy”, PEQUOD, Spring, 1976 Essay: "A Living to Fail: The Case of John Berryman.", undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Shapiro, Alan. Typescript of "Far Lamps at Night", an essay on the poetry of J.V. Cunningham, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Shapiro, Alan. Essay “A Living to Fail: The Case of John Berryman.”, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Smith, Janet Adam. "Scott and the Idea of Scotland" (Parts 1 and 2) University Of Edinburgh Journal Spring and Autumn 1964 (Offprints) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Steele, Timothy. "Uncertainties and Rest." Copy of mss. Correspondence from Steele to Davie, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Stegner, Wallace. Robert Frost and Bernand De Voto. California: The Associates of Stanford University Libraries, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Steiner, George. "Real Presences: The Leslie Stephen Memorial Lecture" (Cambridge University Press, 1986) Inscribed. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Stilllman, Michael B. "Memories of Grace Street." (Typescript). Inscribed. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Swann, Charles. "The Author of ‘Mark Rutherford’, or Who Wrote Miriam’s Schooling.” The Yearbook of English Studies Vol. 9, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Trimpi, Wesley. "The Practices of Historical Interpretation and Nashe's 'Brightnesse Falls from the Ayre'". Journal of English and Germanic Philology Vol. LXVI, No. 4. October, 1967. (Offprint) Inscribed. “The Definition and Practice and Literary Studies.” New Literary History Vol. II, No. 1 Autumn, 1970. Inscribed., 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Wiltshire, Susan. "Introduction: The Classical Tradition in the South" and "Jefferson, Calhoun, and the Slavery Debate: The Classics and the Two Minds of the South.” Southern Humanities Review (Auburn, 1977) Inscribed by Susan Wiltshire to Greg Miller, May, 1979., 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Oversize
  - Davie, Donald and Doreen Davie. Romanesque Brevagna. Original book by Donald and Doreen Davie. String-tied in red paper boards, one of two sets.
  - A Garland of Many Years. Poems for Doreen Davie from her loving husband., 1974 December 10